Guide to the Internationale Situationniste Records, 1968-1972
Department of Special Collections
Internationale Situationniste Records,
1968-1972
Special Collections M0889
Internationale Situationniste
2.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1991.
Scope and Content
Includes manuscripts, handouts, correspondence, monographs, movement publications, reprints, pamphlets, posters, stickers, and collages.
Access Terms
Alegro, Daniel.; Brinton, Maurice.; Camatte, Jacques.; Debord, Guy.; Gregoire, Roger.; Katz, Leandro.; Khayati, Mustapha.; Lakhdar, Lafif.; Lallement, Jimmy.; Lamphear, Linda.; Riesel, Rene.; Vaneigem, Raoul.; Vienet, Rene.; Voyer, J.P.; Student movements.; Students--Political activity--France.; France--History--1945-; France--Intellectual life--20th century.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts, handouts, correspondence
  - Raoul Vaneigem: (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Trabajo sobre el buen vivir para uso de las jovenes generaciones, Spanish transl. of Traité de savoir-vivre..., Manuscript.
    - Experiments in Daily Life #1, MA: Council for Experiments in Daily Life., Handout.
    - Some advice concerning generalised self-management, transl. by C. Whitbread from S.I. #12, 1969., Handout, 3 copies.
  - Horelick and Verlann: (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To the French section of the Situationist International, letter of rupture addressed to Guy Debord, R. Vienet, R. Riesel... and Sanguinetti. Brooklyn:, 1971.
      Handout.
    - Strobe light tyrannies of adolescence and letter. NY: Feb. 1970., Handout and letter.
  - J.P. Voyer: (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lettre ouverte aux citoyens du F.H.A..R. Paris: Institut de Préhistoire Contemporaine, Nov. 1971., Offset handout.
    - Open Letter to the Citizens of the Homosexual Front of Revolutionary Action. NY: Create Situations. Transl. manuscript of above handout.
  - The Actuality of the Question of Political Propaganda and Organization among Revolutionaries in 1971., Mimeograph handout, 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - How to Use Reich. English transl., Handout. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rene Riesel with G. Debord and R. Vaneigem: (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Councils and Councilists Organizations: Basic Facts. Transl. from International Situationist #12, Sept. 1969, by Create Situations, NY., Manuscript plus 2 copies.
  - Jimmy Lallement. For a new world. Angers, 1971., Manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roger Grégoire and Linda Lanphear. To the readers of Black & Red. Paris, 1971., Handout. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lafif Lakhdar and Mustapha Khayati. Waiting for the Massacre: 24 Theses on the present situation. Transl. by Create Situations, NY from French version published in "An-Nudhal, 1970., Manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Dinosaur has a Spear in its Foot and is Rotting: Ireland 1971. 18 theses. Written by Fiends of Lautréamont, Nov. 1971., Handout. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - On the Dinosaur Theses of the Friends of Lautréamont. Signed Cunneen/Verlaan. NY: Create Situations, March 1972. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Guy Debord. Society of the Spectacle. English transl. manuscript assigned to the members of the S.I. American branch in response to the Black & Red version. Complete, theses 1-221. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Guy Debord. La Sociedad del Espectáculo. Spanish transl. manuscripts assigned to members of the S.I. American and Spanish branches: (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Capitolo 1, La Separación Consumada. Tesis 1 al 34, 2 versions.
    - Capitolo 2, La Mercancia Como Espectáculo. Tesis 35 al 53. 2 different versions, one is handwritten with message in Dutch.
    - Capitolo 3, Unidad y División Dentro de la Apariencia. Tesis 54 al 72.
    - Capitolo 4, El Proletariado Como Sujeto y Como Representación. Tesis 73 al 124, 2 copies.
    - Capitolo 5 - Missing.
  - Guy Debord. La Sociedad del Espectáculo. Spanish transl. manuscripts assigned to members of the S.I. American and Spanish branches: (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Capitolo 6, Tiempo Espectacular. Tesis 147 al 179.
    - Capitolo 7, La Organización de Territorio. Tesis 165 al 179.
    - Capitolo 8, Negación y Consumo en la Cultura. Tesis 180 al 211, manuscript with corrections.
    - Capitolo 8, Negación y Consumo en la Cultura. Tesis 180 al 211, Published version of this chapter. NY: Vanishing Triangle Press, 1972.
    - Capitolo 9, La Ideología Materializada. Tesis 212 al 221, 2 copies.
  - Guy Debord. La Societé du Spectacle. Full length documentary film. Paris: Institut de Préhistoire Contemporaine. Publicity literature for film., 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Monographs
  - Subseries A. Guy Debord
    - Contre le Cinéma, Institut Scandinave de Vandalisme Comparé / Bibliothèque d'Alexandrie, 1964., 90 p. Pict. Wrappers. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Society of the Spectacle, Detroit: Black & Red, 1970., Pict. wrappers (detached). (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Society of the Spectacle, Detroit: Black & Red, 1973., 2nd printing. Pict. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      wrappers.
    - La Société du spectacle, Paris: Editions Champ Libre, with original 6 p. folded advertisement flyer. (1st published Paris: Buchet Chastel, 1967). (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Pict. wrappers.
  - Subseries B. Raoul Vaneigem
    - Traité de savoir-vivre à l'usage des jeunes generations, Paris: Gallimard, 1968. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      **Has not been returned to Mr. Katz from loan to the "Situationist International 1957-1972" exhibition (Centre Pompidou, Paris; Institutes of Contemporary Art, London and Boston). If it surfaces, it will be forwarded to Stanford University Libraries.**
    - Treatise on Living for the Use of the Young Generation, (transl. of 1st section of Traité de savoir-vivre...) NY: Situationist International, American section, ca. 1969., Printed wrappers. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Revolution of everyday life - part 2, (transl. of 2d section of Traité de savoir-vivre...) NY: Create Situations, ca. 1970., Black printed wrappers, lilac paper, 1st ed. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Revolution of everyday life - part 2, (transl. of 2d section of Traité de savoir-vivre...) NY: Create Situations, ca. 1970., Printed wrappers, white paper, 2nd ed. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Totality for kids, (transl. from French by C. Gray and P. Vissac), NY: Situationist International, ca. 1970. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Structure of Appearances, (transl. section of Traité de savoir-vivre... p. 126-133) NY, ca. 1969., 3 p. offset. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Situationist International movement publications
  - Leaving the 20th century "The Incomplete work of the Situationist International." Transl. and ed. by Christopher Gray. London: Free Fall Productions, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Printed wrappers.
  - Situationist International, no. 1. NY, June 1969. Review of the American section of the SI. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Vienet, René. Enragés et situationistes dans le mouvement des occupations, Paris: Témoins Gallimard, 1968. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Internationale situationniste 1958-69, "bulletin central édité par les sections de l'internationale situationniste." Amsterdam: Van Gennep, 1970., Silver wrappers. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Situationist International anthology, Transl. and ed. by Ken Knabb. Berkeley: Bureau of Public Secrets, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Situationist Times, International edition -, 2 unnumbered issues (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Situationist Times 3, International British edition, Holland: Jacqueline de Jong, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Situationist Times 4, International edition, Paris: Jacqueline de Jong, Oct. 1963. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Situationist Times 5, International edition, Paris: Jacqueline de Jong, Dec. 1964. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - On the Poverty of Student Life, NY: Situationist International. ca. 1969., Pict. wrappers. 24 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Poor and the Superpoor, NY: Create Situations, 1971., Pict. wrappers. 46 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Beginning of an Epoch, NY: Create Situations, 1971., Pict. wrappers. 64 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Veritable Split - Public circular of the Situationist International. London: B.M. Piranha, 1974., Printed wrappers. 125 p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Velli, Michael. Manual for Revolutionary Leaders. Detroit: Black & Red, 1972., Pict. wrappers. 271 p. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Perlman, Fredy. Incoherence of the intellectual. Detroit: Black & Red, 1970., Pict. wrappers. 117 p. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - En Cuestión No. 1, Buenos Aires: Internacional Situacionalista, 1971., Pict. wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Omphalos. London, n.d., Pict. wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Diversion Nr.1, Ed. by Jon Horelick. New York, 1973., Gold wrappers. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Voyer, Jean-Pierre. Reich, modo de empleo. Institut de Préhistoire Contemporaine. Transl. into Spanish by Tita Carrión. Berkeley, 1973., 8 p. staple bound pamphlet, 4 copies in different colored papers. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Reprints and Pamphlets - from SI and offspring groups
  - Enragés and the situationists in the Occupation Movement, France, May-June 1968. By René Viénet. England: Tiger Papers Publications., 27 p. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Self-realisation, communication and participation," reprint chapter from Leaving the 20th Century. By Raoul Vaneigem. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Traffic," reprint chapter from Leaving the 20th Century. By Raoul Vaneigem. I.S. No. 6, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "End of Prehistory." 2 advertisement pamphlets for 2 90-minute cassettes from radio broadcast, Berkeley, 1972. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brinton, Maurice. The Irrational in Politics, Detroit: Black & Red, 1975., Pict. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    wrappers. 95 p.
  - Lip and the self-managed counter-revolution, from Negation # 3. Detroit: Black & Red, 1975., Pict. wrappers. 95 p. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Camatte, Jacques. Wandering of Humanity, Detroit: Black & Red, 1975., Pict. wrappers. 64 p. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1917 to 1921, Detroit: Black & Red, 1972., Pict. wrappers. 86 p. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Root, Branch & Mammal no. 2 - a monthly bulletin of animal discourse," Vermont: Center for the Study of Cultural Morphology & Mutation, ca. 1970. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series V: Posters, Stickers and Collages
  - "Negotión y Consumo en la Cultura." Ch. VIII of Guy DeBord's Society of the Spectacle., Metal and paper plates; 3 cover plate negatives. (Box 4)
  - Original collage by Leandro Katz. "Negotión y Consumo en la Cultura." For front cover of T.R.V.T. publication, 1971. (Box 4)
  - Original collage by Leandro Katz. "Negotión y Consumo en la Cultura." For back cover of T.R.V.T. publication, 1971. (Box 4)
  - Documento No. 1. By Daniel Alegro, Grupo "En Cuestión," Argentina, 1971. New York: The Vanishing Triangle Press - T.R.V.T. 1971, Pict. wrappers, plastic covers. (Box 4)
  - Original photo novel collage by Leandro Katz. Documento No. 1. For cover of T.R.V.T. publication., Signed by Katz. (Box 4)
  - "Hello Man! I'm a Picture of a Woman." New York: Create Situations, S.I., NY branch, Aug. 1970., Sticker, 2 copies. (Box 4)
  - "A Flash of Insight into Maoist 'Correct Thought'.", Sticker. (Box 4)
  - "... Create Situations that Go Beyond the Point of No Return." NY: Create Situations, ca. 1969., Poster. (Box 4)
  - "You'll Want to Read This." NY: Speedwrath., Subway car poster. (Box 4)
  - Original photo novel cover collage by Leandro Katz. "Latinamerica and I have a Little Nest in Switzerland." New York: T.R.V.T., 1970. (Box 4)